Waft your waves, ye waters!
Carry your crests to the cradle!
- Are you watching alone?
- With you there'd be two of us
- Let's see how you watch
- Safe from you
- Heiaha! Sprightly sisters!
- Help me capture Woglinde
Badly you guard the gold
Watch better or you'll repent
Hey, nymphs!
How inviting you look
From Nibelheim I'd gladly draw near
if you'd but come down to me
See who's spying on us!
- Ugh! How frightful!
- Guard the gold!
Father warned us of a foe
- You up there!
- What do you want?
Do I spoil your sport by staring?
If you'd come down, the Nibelung
would freely frolic with you
Is he in jest?
How brightly you shine!
My arms would love to enfold
one of you
Now I laugh at my fears!
Our foe is in love!
- Lascivious beast!
- We'll teach him!
- She's coming down
- Come close to me, then!
Loathsome slime!
My hands and feet are slipping!
Damp fills my nostrils
Curse this sneezing!
My wooer comes spluttering!
Be my love, fairest child!
Woo me up here!
Alas, come back!
What you manage is hard for me
Climb to the bottom!
You'll catch me there!
- Better down there!
- But now up again!
How can I catch this bashful fish?
Wait, false one!
Hey, beloved!
Don't you hear me?
Is it me you're calling?
Turn to me.
Do not heed Woglinde!
You are far lovelier.
That shy one is much too sly
Come down if you'd delight me
- Am I close to you now?
- Not close enough!
Twine your arms around me ...
... that I may touch your neck ...
... and caress your soft breast
If you're longing for love ...
... let's see what you look like
Ugh, you hairy horror!
Swarthy, sulphurous dwarf!
Find yourself a sweetheart
who'd suffer you!
Though I don't please,
I'll hold you
Fast then, or I'll fly
Perfidious child! Frigid fish!
If I don't seem handsome,
suave and sprightly ...
... then flirt with the eels!
So soon disheartened?
You've courted two
If you asked the third ...
... blissful balm she'd bestow
A sweet song sounds in my ear
How good there are more of you!
There must be one I'd please
If I'm to believe you, come down!
How stupid you are, sisters!
Don't you think him handsome?
I think them stupid and ugly
since I saw you, the fairest
Sing on. That song tempts my ear
My heart hammers and shivers
in pleasure at such praise
Your grace rejoices my eyes
Your smile rejoices my spirit
- Dearest of men!
- Sweetest of maids!
- Would you but favour me!
- I'd hold you for ever
Might I ever see your piercing gaze
and clasp your bristly beard!
Might your wiry hair flow
round me for ever
Might I see only
your toad-like form ...
... and hear your croaking voice!
- Do you mock me?
- How justly at the song's end!
Alas! Woe is me!
Has the third betrayed me too?
You sly, sluttish wenches!
Do you feed only on fraud?
Heia! For shame, gnome!
Don't scold down there!
Listen to what we tell you!
Why did you not secure
the maid for whom you yearned?
We are faithful
to the wooer who holds us fast
Seize on us and do not fear.
In the water we cannot escape
Through me an ardent fire burns
Fury and longing surge
through my spirit
Though you laugh, I long for you
and one of you must yield to me!
If this fist could seize one!
Look, the sun laughs in the depths
Through the green waters
she greets the sleeper
Now she kisses his eyes open
See, he smiles in the light
His rays flood through the waters
Rhinegold! Dazzling delight!
Your glow spreads a glorious light
Awake, friend, to joy!
The river flashes as we dance
and sing in our joyous sport
Rhinegold! Heiajahei!
What is it that gleams there?
Whence come you that you have
never heard of the Rhinegold?
Does the gnome know nothing of the
eyes of gold that wake and sleep?
Of the star in the depths
that shines through the waves?
See how we bask in its glow!
If you wish, sport with us!
Gold only for games
would be little use to me
He would not scorn the gold
if he were aware of its wonders
He could win the world's wealth
if from the Rhinegold ...
... he fashioned the ring that
confers immeasurable might
Father ordered us ...
... to guard the treasure
No cheat should ravish it.
So hush, you chatterers!
Do you not know to whom alone
it is given to shape the gold?
Only he who forswears ...
... love's power and delight
Only he can attain the magic
to fashion the gold into a ring
Then we are secure.
Everything that lives wants love
No one will reject it
Least of all that lascivious gnome
I do not fear him as I found him.
His passion almost burned me
Like a brand in the waves,
he was sizzling with love
Dear gnome, why don't you laugh?
In the glow how fair you shine!
Come, beloved, laugh with us!
The world's wealth
I could win through you?
If I cannot extort love,
can I by cunning attain pleasure?
Mock on!
The Nibelung nears your toy!
Save yourselves!
The gnome has gone crazy!
Love has sent him mad!
Are you still not afraid?
Then coquette in the dark!
I will put out your light ...
... wrench the gold from
the rock ...
... forge the ring of revenge
Hear me, waves!
Thus I curse love!
Stop, thief!
- Rescue the gold!
- Help!
Wotan, husband, awake!
Gate and door guard
the sacred hall of my joy
Man's honour, eternal might
extend to endless fame
Up, leave dream's deceit!
Rouse yourself and reflect!
The everlasting work is done
The god's stronghold soars
resplendent
As in my dreams I desired it ...
... as my will directed ...
... strong and fair it stands ...
... sublime, superb!
Do you delight in what I dread?
I fear for Freia
Reckless man, recall the price
The fort is finished:
forfeit is the pledge
I well know the terms
By a contract ...
... I tamed those
that built this abode
Now it stands, thanks to them.
As to the price, pay that no heed
Outrageous levity!
Had I known of your contract,
I would have prevented the fraud
You men kept women away
to deal alone with the giants
Shamelessly you bartered
Freia, my lovely sister
What do you men hold sacred ...
... when you thirst for power?
Was Fricka free from thirst ...
... when she begged
for the building?
Concern over his constancy ...
... makes me ponder how
to keep him ...
... when he is drawn to roam
A stately dwelling might tempt you
to tarry here and rest
You thought only of defences
to increase your power
Only to arouse storms ...
... did this castle arise
You wished to keep me in the castle
But even as a god confined,
I must win the outside world
All who live love roaming
I cannot relinquish this sport
Unloving man!
For the toys of dominion ...
... would you stake
love and a woman's worth?
To win you for my wife
I sacrificed one of my eyes
I prize women
more than pleases you!
And I will not yield Freia.
I never intended it so
Then protect her now!
Save me, sister!
Protect me, brother!
From yonder mountain Fasolt would
come to force me away
Let him threaten!
Did you not see Loge?
You always trust that trickster!
Much harm he's already done us ...
... yet ever again he ensnares you
When courage suffices
I ask none for help
But to use foes' jealousy ...
... only Loge's cunning will serve
He promised to deliver Freia
I now rely on him
And he forsakes you!
The giants approach
Where loiters your helper?
Where linger my brothers ...
... who should bring help, since
my brother-in-law abandons me?
Donner, help! Come hither, Froh!
They who betrayed you
have all gone to ground
Sleep sealed your eyes ...
... while we two built the fort
Toiling yet untiring,
we heaped up massive stones
There stands what we raised ...
... brightly shining in
the light of day
Now pass in and pay us our fee
Name your price, my men
Is your memory so weak?
Freia the fair ...
... it was agreed we should
take home
Think of some other reward
Are you planning treachery?
Are the marks of solemn compact
on your spear but sport to you?
Brother, do you see the swindle?
Son of light, beware!
Hold firm to your bond!
What you are,
you are only by contracts
Limited and defined is your power
You have more wisdom than we
You bound us to keep peace
I will curse all your wisdom
and flee from your peace ...
... if you do not keep your bond!
A simple giant thus counsels you.
Wise one, weigh his words!
How cunning to take in earnest
what was agreed only in jest
The lovely goddess,
of what use is her charm to you?
Do you mock us?
You, who rule by beauty ...
... radiant race, foolishly you
strive for towers of stone ...
... and pledge woman's beauty!
We toil away
to win a winsome woman ...
... who will live with
us poor creatures
And do you now upset our bargain?
Cease your idle chatter!
Custody of Freia serves little ...
... but to carry her off
is worth much
Golden apples grow in her garden
Only she knows how to tend them
By eating the fruit, her kindred
are endowed with eternal youth
Sick and wan ...
... they will waste away
if they are forced to forego Freia
Let her be taken from their midst!
Loge delays too long
- Your answer!
- Another fee!
Only Freia!
Follow us!
Help from these ruffians!
To me, Freia!
Froh will protect you
Fasolt and Fafner, have you felt
my hammer's heavy blow?
Why do you threaten?
We only want our wages
Many a time have I paid
giants their due
The payment I'll weigh
in full measure
Hold, hothead!
My spearshaft protects bonds
Spare your hammer's haft!
Alas! Wotan forsakes me!
Do I understand you, cruel man?
Loge at last!
Is this how you hasten
to right your evil bargain?
What bargain?
That which you contracted?
House and hearth delight me not
Donner and Froh
are dreaming of shelter
A stately home was Wotan's wish
House and court, hall and keep,
the glorious fortress now stands
I made sure that all was solid
I found Fasolt and Fafner reliable
Every stone was firm in place
I was not idle, as were many here!
Take care how you betray
your only friend among the gods!
Speak and counsel well!
When those who built the castle
stipulated Freia as payment ...
... I agreed because you undertook
to redeem the noble pledge
To consider how to release her -
that I promised
But how could I promise what never
existed nor could succeed?
What a treacherous knave
you trusted!
Your name is Loge. I call you liar
I'll quench your fire!
To cover their disgrace they
revile me
Leave my friend in peace!
Loge's counsel is of richer weight
when he delays in giving it
- No delays! Pay up!
- We're waiting for our wages
Listen, shifty one!
Where have you been roving?
Ingratitude is always Loge's lot!
Concerned but for you ...
... I ransacked the earth
to find a substitute for Freia
In vain I searched
In the whole wide world
nothing is so rich ...
... that a man will accept it in
lieu of woman's beauty and delight
Wherever there is life and being,
in water, earth and air ...
... I asked and sought of all ...
... what would a man think mightier
than woman's beauty and delight?
My question was derided
Nothing gives up love
and womankind
Only one I saw
had forsworn love for gold
The Rhine's children
bewailed their plight to me
The Nibelung, night-Alberich,
stole from them the Rhinegold
He now esteems it
earth's most precious prize ...
... greater than woman's grace
The daughters appeal to you,
Wotan ...
... to bring the thief to justice
Give them the gold back ...
... to remain their own for ever
I promised them to tell you this
Now Loge has kept his word
You are mad, if not malicious!
You see me in trouble myself.
How can I bring others help?
I grudge the gnome this gold.
Much harm he has already done us
New mischief will the Nibelung plot
if the gold gives him power
You there, Loge!
Of what great value is the gold?
It is a toy for laughing children
But were it fashioned into a ring
it would bestow supreme power ...
... and win its master the world
I have heard of the Rhine's gold
Its glow hides runes of riches
A ring would give unbounded power
Would the glittering gems
serve as adornment for women?
A wife could ensure
her husband's fidelity ...
... with the ornament dwarfs forge,
toiling in the power of the ring
Could my husband win this gold?
To control this ring seems wise
But how can I learn the art
of forging this gem?
A spell turns the gold into a ring
No one knows it
But anyone can acquire it
who renounces love
That you will not. You are too late
Alberich did not hesitate
He gained the power of the spell
The ring became his!
The dwarf will control us all ...
... if the ring is not
wrested from him
I must have the ring!
It is easily won without
cursing love
Child's play!
- Tell us, how?
- Theft!
What a thief stole,
you steal from the thief
Could possessions
be more easily acquired?
But Alberich guards with guile
You must act subtly to return ...
... the Rhinemaidens' gold ...
... for that is what they beg
Rhinemaidens?
What is this to me?
I wish to know nothing of them.
Many a man, to my sorrow ...
... have they lured
with their sport
That gold is worth more than Freia
Eternal youth he gains
who commands it by gold's magic
Hear, Wotan, what we have to say!
Freia may stay with you in peace
We giants would be satisfied
with the Nibelung's gold
Can I give you what I do not own?
The castle was hard to build
It will be easy for you with craft
to fetter the Nibelung firmly
Shall I exert myself
to fetter the foe for you?
Come, girl! Follow us
till we receive your ransom
Till evening we will hold
her as hostage
We shall return
If as ransom the Rhinegold
is not ready ...
... she will go with us for ever!
Sister! Brothers! Help!
- After them!
- Let us break everything!
Save me!
Over stock and stone
they stride ...
... through the ford
across the Rhine
Heia! How the louts lurch along!
Only at Riesenheim will they pause
On what does Wotan brood?
How goes it
with the glorious gods?
Does a mist deceive me?
How anxious and pale
you've become!
The light has faded
from your eyes!
Courage, Froh,
it is but early yet!
From your hand the hammer falls!
How is it with Fricka?
Is she displeased
with Wotan's grey gloom?
Alas! What has happened?
My hand drops
My heart falters
Hear what it is you lack!
You have not yet eaten
Freia's fruit
The golden apples in her garden ...
... made you hearty and young ...
... when you ate them every day
She is now a hostage
On the branches the fruit withers
It irks me less.
To me Freia was always niggardly
I am only half as godlike
as you glorious ones!
But you staked all on the fruit.
This the giants knew well
Without the apples ...
... old, grey, and haggard,
the scorn of all the world ...
... the race of gods will die!
Wotan, husband, unhappy man!
See how your thoughtlessness
has brought disgrace on us all
Loge, come down to Nibelheim
I will procure the gold
The Rhinemaidens appealed to you.
Can they hope for a hearing?
Silence! We must deliver Freia
As you command,
I will lead you down.
- Shall we go through the Rhine?
- Not through the Rhine!
Through the sulphurous cleft?
Slip into it with me!
Wait here till evening
Our loss of youth
I'll banish with redeeming gold!
- Farewell, Wotan!
- Good luck!
Return soon to your anxious wife!
Come here, crafty dwarf!
You shall be pitilessly pinched ...
... if you haven't finished
the fine-wrought gold on time
Let me go! It's ready as ordered
- Why are you so slow to show it?
- Lest something was lacking
- What is not ready?
- Here ... and there
Give me the work!
See, scoundrel,
everything finished!
Did the simpleton seek
to deceive ...
... and keep for himself the object
my craft taught him how to forge?
The helmet fits.
Will the spell work too?
"Night and mist, like to no one!"
Can you see me, brother?
Where are you? I cannot see you
Then feel me, rascal! Take that
for your thieving thoughts!
Thank you, stupid!
Your work has stood the test
Nibelungs, bow down to Alberich!
Now he is watching you everywhere
and rest is refused you
Work for him though he is unseen
You are his vassals for ever!
Listen for him, he is near,
the Lord of the Nibelungs
Here is Nibelheim.
What fiery sparks are flashing?
What is that among the rocks?
Why are you whimpering?
Hey, Mime! What torments you so?
Leave me in peace!
More yet, I would help you, Mime!
I must obey my own brother
who brought these bonds on me
What gave him the power
to bind you?
Cunning Alberich wrought himself
a ring from the Rhine's gold
With it he has overcome us,
the Nibelungs' nocturnal race
Carefree smiths, once we created
ornaments for our women ...
... and lightly laughed at our work
This villain compels us to creep
into caverns and toil for him
Through the ring his greed divines
where a new gleam is concealed
We have to dig it out, melt the
booty and forge the cast ...
... to pile up our master's hoard
Your idleness brought on his ire?
On me he forced the heaviest task
He bade me forge and weld a helmet
I noted what power
lay in the work I fashioned
I wanted to keep the helmet
and escape from Alberich's sway ...
... perhaps get him in my power ...
... and snatch the ring so that
I might be free and he my slave!
Why did you not succeed?
Though I fashioned the work ...
... I did not guess
the spell aright
He who planned the work
and snatched it from me ...
... has taught me
what cunning lay in the helmet
He vanished from my sight,
but unseen his arm raised weals
That's what thanks I earned!
- Our capture will not be easy
- He will fall with your cunning
Who are you, then, strangers?
Friends. We will free the Nibelungs
Beware! Alberich draws near
We'll wait here for him
Idle herd, pile up the hoard!
Put down the treasure!
Must I help?
Who is there?
Here, scamp! Have you
been chattering to these tramps?
Be off, idler! Back to your bench!
Out of here, all of you!
Find me gold from the new veins!
My whip waits
for those that don't dig deep!
I am everywhere
though none can tell where
Are you still lingering?
Still loitering?
Tremble, abject throng!
Obey the master of the ring!
What do you want here?
From Nibelheim's land of night
we have heard new rumours
Mighty marvels Alberich works.
Greed brought us as guests to gorge
Envy led you, that I well know
Do you know me well?
Who am I that you should snarl?
In your cave Loge smiled on you,
gave light and warming flames ...
... and fired your forge
I am your kinsman, was your friend.
You show little thanks
Loge smiles now with elves of light
If, false one, you're their friend
as you once were mine ...
... I have nothing to fear
- You can have faith in me
- In faithlessness not fidelity
But dauntlessly I defy you all!
Your power lends you assurance
Great has grown your strength
Do you see the hoard heaped up?
I never yet saw one so enviable
That is today's paltry pile.
It will increase in the future
But Nibelheim is joyless ...
... and treasure can buy nothing
Nibelheim's night serves me
to create and conceal treasure
With the hoard in the cave
I intend to work wonders
I will win the world for my own
How will you start on that?
You who aloft in the breeze
live, laugh and love ...
... all you gods I'll grip
in my golden grasp!
As I renounced love ...
... all shall renounce it!
Allured by gold,
for gold alone shall you hunger
On radiant peaks you live in bliss
The black gnome you despise,
you eternal revellers!
Beware!
When you men serve my might the
dwarf will take his pleasure ...
... with your pretty women,
though love does not smile on him
Did you hear?
Beware when the Nibelung horde ...
... rises from the depths
to the light!
- Blasphemous fool!
- What?
Keep your head!
Faced with Alberich's work
who would not feel wonder?
If you win, with your treasure,
all you demand ...
... I must acclaim you
the mightiest
Moon, stars, and radiant sun ...
... can do no other but serve you
But ...
... I deem it significant
that those who heap the hoard ...
... obey you ungrudgingly
Boldly you fingered a ring ...
... before which they trembled
But if a thief by stealth ...
... snatched the ring?
How would you guard yourself?
Loge thinks himself most artful
Others seem stupid to him
That I should need his counsel,
the thief would rejoice to hear
I conceived the concealing helmet
and had Mime fashion it for me
The helmet allows me
to change my shape at will
No one can see me, yet I am
everywhere
I can live safe even from you ...
... kind, considerate friend!
I have seen many strange things,
but never witnessed such a wonder
I cannot credit this unique work
Were this possible,
your power would last for ever
- Do you think I lie like Loge?
- Until I see for myself
The fool is bursting with wisdom
Now may envy devour you!
In what shape shall I appear?
Whatever you will
Strike me dumb with astonishment!
Giant serpent, curl and coil!
Oh, do not swallow me!
Spare Loge's life!
Good, you villain! How quickly
the dwarf turned to a dragon!
Do you believe me now?
My trembling testifies to it
Now that I have seen it
I readily believe the marvel
But can you make yourself tiny?
That would be the subtle way
to escape danger
But that would be too hard!
How small shall I be?
So that a crevice might hold you
where a toad timidly hides
Nothing simpler!
Watch me!
Crawl, crooked grey toad!
Seize it quickly!
- I am captured!
- Hold him till I tie him!
Up we go. There he will be ours
Sit tight there, kinsman!
Look, there lies the world
that you wanted to win
What spot, tell me,
will you allow for my sty?
Rogue! Ruffian! Loosen my
bonds or you'll rue this outrage!
You are caught in my chains
You fancied the world lay
in your power
Wretch, you cannot deny it!
To free you a ransom is demanded
Dolt I am, to trust this trick!
Terrible vengeance I vow!
First you must set yourself free
To a fettered man
no free soul makes amends
If you relish thoughts of revenge,
first think about the ransom
- Say what it is you want
- The treasure and your gold
Greedy gang of rogues!
But if I keep the ring
I could spare the treasure
New wealth would soon be won
at the ring's command
I shall not pay too dear
if the lesson costs only baubles
- Will you yield the treasure?
- Loosen my hand and I'll summon it
I have called the Nibelungs
I hear them hauling
the hoard from the depths
Now loosen my bonds!
Not until all has been paid
Oh humiliation that my slaves
should see me captive!
Bring it in as I command!
Pile the hoard into a heap!
Don't glance over here!
Quick there, quick
Then get back to your labour!
Woe betide if I find you idle!
I am following at your heels
I have paid. Now let me depart
And the helmet that Loge holds,
now kindly give back to me
This belongs to the ransom
Accursed thief!
But patience!
He who made it can make another
Mine is the might that Mime obeys
Yet it's hard to leave
my weapon to my foes
Alberich has left you everything.
Now, bullies, loosen my bonds!
Shall I untie him?
A golden ring rests on your finger
- That belongs to the hoard
- The ring?
- To be freed you must forfeit it
- My life, but not the ring!
I require the ring.
With your life do what you will!
I lose limb and life
if I must lose the ring too
Hand and head, eye and ear
are not more my own than this!
You call the ring your own?
Are you raving, shameless gnome?
From whom did you take the gold
from which you made the ring?
Was it your own,
that you stole it from the depths?
Ask the Rhine's daughters ...
... whether they gave you
the gold you robbed
Base trickery! Vile deceit!
Do you throw on me the blame
for what you so dearly desired?
Gladly you would have robbed
the Rhine of its gold ...
... had you so easily
found the way to forge it!
How well it worked for you ...
... that I, in shame and fury ...
... gained the terrible magic
whose work now gladdens you!
Must this fatal, fearful deed ...
... serve you as a royal toy,
my curse serve for your pleasure?
Take heed, haughty god!
If I sinned it was against myself
But you sin against all that was,
is and shall be ...
... if you seize my ring!
Surrender the ring!
No right to it can you prove
Crushed!
Shattered!
Of wretches the wretchedest slave!
Now I possess what will make me
the mightiest of mighty lords!
Is he to go?
Set him free!
Slink off home! No knot holds you
Am I free?
Truly free?
Then thus I give you
my freedom's first greeting!
Since by curse it came to me,
accursed be this ring!
Since its gold gave me might ...
... may its magic bring death
to whoever wears it!
It shall gladden no happy man
Its gleam shall light
on no one lucky!
Whoever possesses it
shall be consumed with care ...
... whoever has it not
shall be gnawed with envy!
Each shall itch to possess it,
but none shall find in it pleasure!
Its owner shall guard it
profitlessly
Through it he shall
meet his executioner!
Forfeit to death, faint with fear
shall he be fettered
The length of his life
he shall long to die ...
... the ring's master to
the ring a slave ...
... until again I hold
in my hand what was stolen!
Thus in direst distress ...
... the Nibelung blesses his ring!
Keep it now, guard it well!
My curse you cannot escape!
Did you heed his fond farewell?
Let him give vent to his fury
Fasolt and Fafner are approaching
They are bringing Freia back
- They have returned
- Welcome, brother!
Do you bring good tidings?
We carried out the task.
There lies what will free Freia
From the giants' grasp
our fair one approaches
The breeze breathes on us again
Bliss fills our senses
It would be gloomy to be
for ever separated from her ...
... who gives us perpetual youth
and joyous delight!
Dearest sister!
Are you restored to me?
Do not touch her!
She still belongs to us
At Riesenheim's boundary
we stopped to rest
Honourably we tended
the pledge for the pact
I regret I am returning her ...
... for us to be paid her ransom
The ransom lies ready
Now the gold shall be measured
To do without the woman
saddens us sorely
If she is to be
banished from my mind ...
... the treasure must be so high
that it hides her from my sight!
Freia's form shall be the measure
These poles measure the pledge.
Now fill the space with the hoard
Hurry! The work is repugnant!
- Help me, Froh!
- I'll end Freia's shame
Not so loosely packed!
Fill the measure tightly!
I can still see through it.
Stop up these chinks!
Stand back, clod!
- Keep your hands off!
- Close these crevices!
Deep in me burns my disgrace
Our pure one stands humiliated
Her look mutely pleads for release
Wicked man, to ask this
of a loved one!
Still more!
Rage this rogue rouses in me!
You cur! If you want to measure,
measure yourself against me!
Your din avails you nothing!
Not even to crush you?
Peace!
I think Freia is covered now
The hoard is used up
I still see the gleam of her hair.
Throw that object on the pile!
The helmet too?
- Here with it!
- Let it go!
Are you satisfied?
Freia the fair I see no more
Must I let her go?
Her gaze still gleams on me here,
through a crack
As long as I see those lovely eyes
I cannot tear myself away!
I advise you, stop up this crack!
Can't you see the gold has gone?
By no means. On Wotan's finger ...
... still glints a ring of gold.
Give it here to fill the crack!
What! This ring?
Listen! This gold belongs
to the Rhinemaidens
Wotan will give it back to them
What idle chatter is this?
What I won I'll keep for myself
It goes badly with the promise
I gave the lamenting maidens
Your promise does not bind me.
The ring remains with me
But you must yield it here
I will grant you everything ...
... but for all the world
I will not surrender the ring!
Then our first bargain stands.
Freia follows us for ever!
- Help!
- Give in to them!
- Do not hold back!
- Give up the ring!
Leave me in peace!
The ring I'll not surrender
Yield, Wotan, yield!
Escape from the ring's curse
To dark destruction ...
... its possession dooms you
Who is this woman who threatens?
I know whatever was
Whatever is, whatever shall be ...
... I also see
The eternal world's first
ancestress ...
... Erda warns you
My womb bore three daughters,
conceived before the start of time
What I see, the Norns
nightly tell you
But direst danger
today brings me in person to you
Hear me!
All that is shall come to an end
A dark day dawns for the gods
I charge you ...
... shun the ring!
Mysterious your words sound
Stay that I may know more!
I have warned you
You know enough
Reflect in fear and dread!
If I must fear and dread,
I must seize you and learn all!
What would you do, madman?
Desist, Wotan! Touch not
the noble one. Heed her words!
Listen, you giants! Wait!
You shall be given the gold
Dare I hope so?
Do you think me
truly worth this ransom?
Come to me, Freia!
You are freed
Bought back, restore our youth!
You giants, take your ring!
Stop, greedy! Leave some for me.
A fair division will be best
You longed more for the maid than
for gold, lovesick loon!
I persuaded you to exchange her.
You would not have shared Freia ...
... so I retain more for myself
Do you insult me?
I call on you as judges
Divide the treasure between us
Let him take the treasure.
Only keep the ring!
Back! Mine is the ring!
For it I gave up Freia's gaze
Hands away! The ring is mine!
I hold it. It belongs to me!
Hold it fast in case it falls!
Now blink at Freia's gaze.
The ring you will not touch again!
Terrible now I find the curse
What luck, Wotan! Great your gain
when you won the ring
More it profits now it is taken
See, your foes fell each other
for the gold that you gave up
Yet anxiety weighs upon me
Dread and fear fetter my mind
How to end it Erda must teach me
I must go down to her
Why do you tarry, Wotan?
Does the noble fort not beckon
as it waits to welcome its owner?
I paid for it with unclean wages!
A sultry haze hangs in the air.
Its dull weight oppresses me
I will collect the clouds
in a storm to sweep the sky
Come to me, mists and vapours!
Donner, your master, summons you
As I swing my hammer, hover here!
Misty moisture, hanging haze!
Donner, your master, summons you
Brother, point out the path!
The bridge leads to the fort ...
... light but firm below your feet
Boldly tread its terrorless path!
The sun sheds its evening beams
In its gleam the castle shines
In the radiance of the morning
it stood tenantless ...
... grand and inviting before me
From morn to eve, in care
and anxiety ...
... not lightly was it won
Night draws on
From envy it now offers shelter
Thus I salute the fortress ...
... safe from terror and dread
Wife, follow me
Dwell in Valhalla with me!
What means the name?
Never have I heard it before
What my courage found for me
If it lives on victorious,
it will make its meaning plain
They hasten to their end,
though they think themselves strong
I am almost ashamed
to share their doings
Fancy lures me to transform
myself back into flames
To burn them who tamed me
rather than end with the blind!
It doesn't seem stupid
I'll think it over
Who knows what I'll do?
Rhinegold! Purest gold!
How bright you once shone on us!
What lamenting assails me here?
Give us the gold!
The children of the Rhine
lament their looted gold
Accursed nymphs!
Give us its glory again!
Stop them annoying us!
You in the water, why wail to us?
Hear what Wotan wills for you
No more gleams the gold on you
Henceforth bask in bliss ...
... in the gods' new radiance!
Rhinegold! If but your gleam
still glittered in the deep!
Now only in the depths lie
tenderness and truth
False and faint-hearted
are those who revel above!